so the first technique that we will
consider is tomasulo's algorithm it's
really one of the first techniques for
outof order execution and now it's more
than 40 years old it was used in the old
IBM 360 machines which are now again
more than 40 years old what it does is
it determines which instructions have
inputs ready so that they can go in the
next cycle and which instructions still
have to wait for their inputs to be
produced it also includes a form of
register raming and it is surprisingly
similar to what we actually use today as
far as outof order execution is
concerned so although this is more than
40 years old it actually is very useful
to know how it works because it's kind
of like the first approach so it's
simpler than what we use today but it
really well explains what's going on the
differences between Tomaso's algorithm
and what is used today are only that in
the olden days when tomasulo's algorithm
was implemented they did that only for
floating Point instructions while today
we do it for all instructions also they
had relatively few instructions in the
window that they looking at meaning they
only really looked over some small
number of instructions into the you know
future instructions that need to be
executed while today we look at hundreds
of instructions past the one we are
still executing in the olden days
exception handling for floating Point
instructions was not such a big problem
because they were only considering
really you know execution of kind of
floating Point intensive applications
and uh you know those would be
programmed and so on and you would
usually run one program at a time if
there is an exception you could do some
drastic measures today process include
explicit support for exception handling
that we will see
later so we will first again look at how
the tomasulo algorithm did it and then
we will consider how today's processors
do these additional things